I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
Take your pills later, okay?
Nanti obatnya diminum ya, Bu.
These pills won't make me better.
Obat dokter tidak akan bikin aku sembuh, Pak.
I'm cold.
Dingin, Pak.
-I'm cold. I can't take it. -Mom.
Dingin, aku tidak kuat.
Mom.
Bu.
-I'll rub some oil on you. -Mom.
Pakai minyak kayu putih ya, Bu.
I can't take this anymore, honey. It's happening every night.
Aku tidak bisa kayak gini terus, Pak, tiap malam.
Someone must have cursed me.
Ini pasti dikerjai orang.
What is it?
Kenapa, Bu?
-Mom. -Honey.
Bu!
Honey, are you all right?
Bu, sadar! Bu?
Honey?
Bu!
Honey! Oh God!
Bu. Astagfirullahaladzim.
Honey.
Bu.
No, don't!
Bu! Bu, jangan!
-Honey! Don't! -Mom!
- Ibu!
Honey!
Bu, jangan.
-Honey! -Mom.
- Bu! - Bu…
-Honey. -It hurts!
- Sakit! - Bu!
-Honey! -Mom, it hurts!
- Ibu, sakit!
-It hurts! -Let go of her!
- Lepaskan, Bu!
Come on, Yul, get inside.
Ayo, Yul, masuk.
Yuli.
Yuli.
Wait here, okay?
Yuli tunggu sini, ya?
I'll come back after I take care of your mom, okay?
Bapak akan kembali setelah urus Ibu. Ya?
-Oh my God. Honey? -It hurts.
- Ya Allah, Bu. Bu? - Sakit, Pak.
-It hurts!
- Sakit. - Sakit, Pak!
No!
Jangan!
I'd rather die!
Lebih baik aku mati, Pak!
-No, stay strong! -Please, it hurts.
- Istigfar, Bu! - Tolong. Sakit, Pak.
Honey, what are you doing? No!
Bu, kenapa? Jangan, Bu!
Honey!
Ibu!
Dad?
Bapak?
Dad? Mom?
Bapak? Ibu?
Little girl.
Dik?
Wake up, dear.
Dik, bangun.
Watch your step.
Awas, hati-hati.
Come on.
Yuk.
Dad? Mom?
Bapak? Ibu?
Mom?
Ibu?
Mom!
Ibu!
-You cannot come in. -That's my husband.
- Maaf, Ibu tidak boleh masuk. - Itu suamiku, Pak.
Mom! Dad!
Ibu! Bapak!
-Honey! -Dad!
- Pak! - Bapak!
-Calm down. -Mom.
- Tenang ya. - Ibu.
-Dad. -It's all right. Calm down.
Bapak.
Mom.
Ibu.
You bastard child.
Dasar kau anak selingkuhan.
You just finished cooking, Yuli?
Ini masakan baru jadi, Yul?
Look at the time. What have you been doing?
Sudah jam segini lo. Dari tadi melakukan saja?
The rice, Yuli!
Nasinya, Yuli!
Yes, just a minute.
Ya, Teh, sebentar.
-Where to, Ka? -To the mosque.
- Ke mana, Ka? - Ke surau.
I'll see you later.
Duluan ya, Pak.
Why do you go to the mosque every day? Grandma's sick, you know.
Untuk apa mengaji setiap hari? Oma lagi sakit lo.
Don't you want to stay at home?
Tidak mau di rumah saja?
But I already promised Abuyya.
Tapi Tika sudah janji sama Abuya.
Yuli? Tika, help her.
Yuli? Tika bantu.
Ma'am.
Ibu?
Yuli, where's the sauce?
Yuli, kau belum membuat sambal ya?
I'll make it right after this.
Ya, setelah ini, Teh.
You know my husband can't eat without chili.
Aa Rudi tidak bisa makan kalau tidak ada sambalnya.
It's too hot.
Masih panas.
Have you showered?
Adik kok belum mandi?
It's still hot, idiot!
Masih panas, bego!
I'm sorry.
Maaf, Bu.
Tika?
Tika?
Take care.
Hati-hati.
Auntie, Grandma doesn't like it.
Yah, Bi. Oma tidak suka.
Have a drink, ma'am.
Minum dulu, Bu.
Grandma, I have to go.
Oma, Tika duluan ya.
Dean, take care of Grandma, okay?
Adik, jaga Oma ya.
Dean, you haven't changed your clothes?
Dean, kau belum ganti baju dari tadi?
Come and give me a kiss.
Cium sini coba. Anak Ibu sini, cium.
You smell. Go change.
Bau perengus. Sudah, sana.
Tika!
Tika!
Let's go.
Yuk.
-Have you been waiting long? -No, I'm good.
- Sudah lama menunggu? - Tidak, baru aja.
-You sure? -Yes.
- Baru? - Ya.
In the Quran, Surah Al-Mutaffifin,
Di dalam Al-Qur'an surat Al-Muthafiffin,
Allah SWT said,
Allah SWT berfirman,
"Kallâ inna kitaâbal-fujjari lafî sijjîn."
"Kalla inna kitabal-fujjari lafi sijjin."
That every disobedient act is recorded in the Sijjin.
Bahwa setiap perbuatan durhaka dicatatkan di dalam sijjin.
Wa mâ adrâka mâ sijjîn.
Wa ma adraka ma sijjin.
What is Sijjin?
Apakah itu sijjin?
It goes on to say,
Ya, selanjutnya dikatakan,
Kitâbum marqûm.
"Kitabum marqum."
A book that records every act of our evil deeds.
Kitab yang mencatat setiap perbuatan durhaka kita.
But if it is for pious deeds, our good deeds,
Tapi kalau untuk amal saleh, perbuatan baik kita,
these will be recorded by the angels in the book called Illiyyin.
akan dicatatkan oleh malaikat
Look at that.
Lihat itu.
The house has been empty for a long time.
Rumahnya sudah lama kosong.
Yeah, it's really dark.
Ya juga. Itu gelap banget.
Who used to live there?
Apa? Bekas apa?
-There's a ghost! -What?
- Hantu! - Astagfirullahaladzim.
O spirits,
Roh-roh yang ada di sini,
I have with me some offerings.
di sini ada sajen.
Come and tell me.
Hadir dan beri tahu aku.
Good evening.
Asalamualaikum.
Dean, I already told you not to play with that.
Adik, Teteh sudah bilang, jangan main gituan.
My friend said that if we use this, we can talk to the dead.
Kata teman Dean, kalau kita pakai ini,
How can you even talk to a dead person?
Mana ada orang yang sudah mati bisa diajak bicara?
What's wrong with Grandma?
Oma kenapa?
Gosh.
Aduh. Tika tambahkan bantalnya ya?
Lift your head.
Lehernya angkat dulu.
Aunt Yuli, do you want to try talking to dead people too?
Bi Yuli mau coba bicara sama orang mati juga?
I wanted to at one time.
Dulu mau.
Every time I missed my late father and mother.
Tiap kangen sama Almarhum Bapak dan Ibu.
What is it?
Kenapa?
Please get some oxygen.
Bi, tolong ambil oksigen. Oma kenapa?
-Aunt Yuli, can I leave her with you? -Yes.
- Bi Yuli, titip ya? - Ya.
-I'll go and get Mom. -Okay.
- Tika panggil Ibu dulu.
Tika, hurry up!
Kak Tika, cepat!
Your parents
Bapak dan ibumu layak mati!
Mom?
Bu?
-Mom? -Tika, help me.
Ibu? Kak, bantu.
-Lift her up. -Okay, we'll do that.
- Bangunkan. - Bangunkan saja.
-Inhaler. -Inhaler?
- Inhaler. - Inhaler?
-Inhaler or pills? -Inhaler.
Inhaler atau obat saja?
-Grandma. -Mom?
- Oma. - Bu?
-Grandma?
Bu?
-Mom? Mom.
- Oma? - Bu? Ibu.
What's wrong, Mom?
Ibu kenapa?
Oh no.
Ya ampun.
Mom…
Ibu…
Grandma?
Oma?
Wake up, Mom.
Bangun, Bu.
-Mom? -She's gone.
- Bu? - Bu, sudah tidak ada.
-Mom. -Grandma.
- Bu. - Oma.
-Mom, wake up.
- Bu, bangun.
Grandma.
Oma.
-Mom. -Grandma.
- Ibu. - Oma.
-Grandma. Grandma! -Mom!
- Oma. Oma! - Ibu…
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
Tika, my condolences.
Tika, turut berduka cita ya.
Indeed, we belong to Allah, and to Him we shall return. Stay strong.
Innalillahi wa inna ilaihi rajiun, sabar ya.
-Peace be upon you. -And upon you too.
- Asalamualaikum. - Alaikum salam.
Those who are not family, please leave the room.
Yang bukan muhrim, silakan keluar dulu.
What are you doing here?
Sedang apa kau di sini?
Get out.
Sana, keluar.
Prepare the shroud for my mother.
Siapkan kafan buat Ibu.
Before we pray for her and have her funeral,
Sebelum kita salatkan dan kuburkan bersama,
if anyone wants to kiss her goodbye,
siapa yang ingin mencium, silakan,
don't let your tears fall, okay?
tapi jangan sampai kena air mata, ya?
Idiot!
Goblok!
Eat it.
Makan tidak?
Eat it!
Makan!
-Idiot! -I'm sorry, ma'am!
- Goblok! - Ampun, Bu!
I've fed you, you bastard!
Sudah dikasih makan, dasar anak selingkuhan!
-Eat it! -No.
Makan!
-Here. -No, ma'am, please!
- Ini! - Tidak mau, Bu, ampun!
I'm sorry.
Ampun, Bu.
Sorry for what?
Ampun apaan?
You're already dead.
Ibu sudah mati.
Die, you!
Mati kau!
Yuli.
Yuli!
Oh God!
Astagfirullahaladzim.
You're happy that my mother died, right?
Kau senang ya Ibu meninggal?
My mother has been taking care of you since you were little,
Sudah bagus dari kecil Ibu mengurusmu.
and now you're making a scene in front of her.
Sekarang di depan Ibu, kau malah bertingkah.
You're so ungrateful, Yuli.
Tidak tahu di untung kau, Yul.
Bastard child!
Dasar anak selingkuhan!
Ms. Laras, please calm down.
Bu Laras. Sabar, Bu.
We shouldn't do this in front of the deceased.
Tidak boleh kita seperti itu di depan jenazah.
-Gosh. -Mom.
- Aduh. - Bu…
Mom, let's go.
Bu, ayo.
Mom, why isn't Dad coming home?
Bu, Bapak kok tidak pulang-pulang?
Let's go inside.
Masuk yuk.
No, I'm waiting for Dad.
Tidak mau. Laras mau tunggu Bapak.
Where did he go, Mom?
Bapak ke mana, Bu?
Yuli is the child of an affair.
Si Yuli itu anak selingkuhan.
Look, she doesn't even look like Mrs. Laras.
Lihat itu. Mukanya saja beda sama Bu Laras.
You're right, she looks different.
Ya, Bu, beda banget mukanya.
Rudi, not there.
Aa Rudi, bukan di sana.
That's not where you put it.
Bukan di sana tempatnya.
It's been two months and you still don't get it.
Kau sudah dua bulan tidak pintar-pintar.
Over there.
Sudah, di sana.
They're all placed over there.
Lihat, sudah ditaruh di sana semuanya.
-You said on the shelf. -No, here.
- Tapi katanya di atas. - Tidak, di sini.
-Okay, okay. -Gosh.
- Ya. - Bagaimana ini?
-Right here? -Yes.
- Sini, Mas? - Ya.
-For you. -Okay.
Ini.
-Thank you. -You're welcome.
- Terima kasih Pak. - Ya, sama-sama.
Bye.
Hei.
Don't take that.
Jangan atuh.
We need to give everything to Laras.
Semuanya harus dikumpulkan, kasih ke Teteh.
Yuli?
Yuli?
What is this?
Apa ini?
Is what my mother gave you still not enough?
Memangnya masih kurang ya yang dikasih Ibu kepadamu?
-No, Yono was just… -I can't believe you.
- Bukan, barusan si Yono… - Kau ini jadi orang…
When will it be enough for you?
Kau selalu merasa kurang.
-I was going to give it to you. -Why did Yono give you money?
- Mau dikasih ke Teteh. - Ini kenapa kau dapat dari Yono?
What did you do with Yono?
Apa yang kau lakukan dengan Yono?
Nothing.
Tidak ada apa-apa, Teh.
-What did you and Yono do? -Nothing, this is…
- Apa yang kau lakukan dengan Yono? - Tidak ada, ini…
You slut, you're just like your mother!
Dasar perempuan murahan ya! Sama saja kayak ibumu!
What? What do you want?
Apa? Kenapa maju?
You're gonna talk back to me now?
Berani kau sekarang sama aku, ya?
Just because my mother is no longer around,
Jangan mentang-mentang sekarang Ibu sudah tidak ada,
you think you can fight me, is that so?
lalu kau berani sama aku. Mau melawan, ya?
I don't care that I'm yelling! It's so everyone will know who she is.
Sudah, biarkan saja, Aa, biar semua orang tahu dia siapa.
That's enough.
Sudah. Ya?
You should go.
Sudah, kau ke sana.
Hello, ma'am.
Mari, Bu.
-What do you need? -Sugar.
- Mencari apa? - Gula.
Sugar?
Gula?
Rudi!
Aa Rudi!
Wait a minute, please.
Sebentar ya.
You should eat, Yuli.
Makan dulu, Yul.
Yono.
Yon.
Help me, please.
Tolong aku, Yon.
You wait here.
Kau tunggu di sini.
I'll go alone.
Aku sendiri saja.
Excuse me.
Permisi.
Abah?
Aba?
Miss Yuli?
Neng Yuli?
Come in.
Masuk.
I want to destroy this family
Aku ingin keluarga ini hancur,
just like they destroyed my life.
seperti mereka menghancurkan hidupku.
What about the one before this?
Yang kemarin sudah mati?
Do you want them blind, disabled,
Kau mau mereka buta, cacat,
or dead?
atau mati?
I want them all…
Aku ingin…
dead.
Semuanya mati.
Are you ready for the risk?
Kau sudah siap dengan risikonya?
My eyes are in the universe.
Mataku di alam semesta.
My spirit is in the unseen realm.
Batinku di alam gaib.
I ask forgiveness from all beings.
Aku mohon maaf kepada semua makhluk.
I ask for guidance from those who dwell there.
Aku mohon petunjuk yang ada di sana.
There is one black magic curse that can make your wishes come true.
Ada satu santet yang bisa mewujudkan keinginanmu.
It is very dangerous and deadly.
Santet itu sangat berbahaya dan mematikan.
The ritual requires a fresh corpse
Santet itu butuh mayat yang segar
which isn't 40 days old yet.
dan belum 40 hari.
What if…
Kalau…
the corpse is from the same family, Bah?
jenazahnya masih satu keluarga, bagaimana, Ba?
That's even better.
Itu lebih baik.
-Wait, wait. So heavy. -One, two, three.
- Sebentar. - Satu, dua, tiga.
-Again. -Two, three.
- Lagi. - Dua, tiga.
-Come on. -Come on. Two, three.
- Ayo.
Come on, hurry up, hurry up.
Ayo cepat.
Yono, come on.
Yon, ayo.
Wait, wait.
Sebentar.
One, two, three.
Satu, dua, tiga.
Wait outside.
- Tunggu di luar aja. - Ya, siap.
Blood meets blood.
Darah bertemu darah.
Skin meets skin.
Kulit bertemu kulit.
Flesh meets flesh.
Daging bertemu daging.
Breech blocked by breech.
Sungsang terhalang oleh sungsang.
Black sky, black earth.
Langit hitam, bumi hitam.
I am controlled by my ancestors.
Aku dikendalikan oleh nenek moyangku.
I am controlled…
Aku dikendalikan…
All shall be destroyed before me.
Semua orang hancur di hadapanku.
Destroyed, destroyed, destroyed.
Hancur, hancur, hancur.
I call upon the Queen of Black Magic in the high mountains.
Aku meminta kepada Ratu Santet di gunung tinggi.
I know the Queen always desires something.
Aku tahu Ratu selalu menginginkan sesuatu.
I have brought her favorite offering.
Aku bawakan sesajen kesukaan Ratu.
Accept my command.
Terimalah perintahku
Destroy them all.
untuk menghancurkan semua orang ini.
Their deaths are on you.
Kematian mereka semua ada di tanganmu.
You have to finish everything before this corpse rots.
Kau harus menyelesaikannya sebelum mayat ini membusuk.
You must perform this ritual until it is completed.
Kau harus melakukan ritual ini sampai selesai.
If you don't,
Kalau tidak,
all the black magic will come back to you.
semua santet itu akan berbalik kepadamu.
The jinn really like sinful and misguided people.
Jin sangat menyukai orang-orang yang berdosa dan sesat.
Make sure those people are sinners and that they deserve to die.
Kau pastikan mereka itu pendosa dan pantas mati.
Allah is the Greatest.
Allahu Akbar.
What's the matter?
Kenapa kau, Tik?
I saw Grandma over there.
Tadi ada Oma, Bi, di sana.
On the bed! She really was there!
Di kasur, Bi. Tadi sungguh ada!
You're just imagining things.
Perasaanmu saja.
Go to sleep. It's late.
Sudah, sana tidur. Sudah malam.
You should have been more careful, Tika.
Kenapa tidak hati-hati, Kak?
I think something's really wrong, Mom.
Tapi Tika sungguh merasa ada yang tidak beres, Bu.
How could the photo fall on its own?
Masa tidak ada apa-apa, foto bisa jatuh sendiri?
It's weird.
Aneh, 'kan?
What if it's Grandma?
Jangan-jangan itu Oma?
Yesterday, I tried to talk to Grandma.
Kemarin, Dean coba bicara sama Oma.
Then she answered.
Lalu, Oma menjawab.
Grandma said…
Kata Oma,
"It hurts."
"Sakit."
Don't say that, okay?
Sudah, jangan bicara seperti itu.
Why are you still playing that?
Kau juga kenapa masih main gituan?
I'm serious.
Dean serius.
What if she is really in pain?
Kalo Oma sungguh kesakitan, bagaimana?
Mom, tonight, we're doing the prayers for Grandma, right?
Bu, nanti malam, kita jadi tiga harian untuk Oma?
What's the point of those prayers, Tika?
Tahlilan itu buat apa, Kak?
You said so yourself.
Kau sendiri yang bilang Oma sudah meninggal.
People should be praying for us.
Justru seharusnya kita yang didoakan, Kak.
So we can stay strong.
Biar ikhlas.
Yes, but there's nothing wrong with praying for Grandma too, right, Mom?
Ya, tapi mengirim doa buat Oma juga tidak ada salahnya, 'kan, Bu?
So she can rest easy there too, okay?
Biar Oma juga tenang di sana. Ya?
You handle it.
Kau atur sajalah ya?
Yuli.
Yuli.
I've been calling for you for a while.
Aku memanggilmu dari tadi, tapi kau baru muncul.
Look at that.
Lihat itu.
Do I have to sort it all out myself?
Masa harus aku sendiri yang bereskan itu semua?
For the prayers tonight, if you need anything,
Nanti buat tiga hariannya Oma, kalau kau butuh apa-apa,
just tell Aunt Yuli.
suruh Bi Yuli saja.
Let her take care of it.
Biar dia yang mengurus.
Okay.
Ya.
But I can't today.
Aku tidak bisa hari ini.
Where are you going?
Mau ke mana kau?
-Aren't you going to the shop? -I have things to do.
- Tidak ke toko? - Ada urusan.
What's wrong with you, Yuli?
Ada apa denganmu, Yul?
You don't want to work.
Kau kerja tidak mau,
You don't want to take care of the prayers.
mengurus tahlilan tidak mau.
You've really been acting up since my mother passed away.
Benar-benar melunjak sejak Ibu tiada.
Yuli.
Yuli.
-There she goes again! -Mom, it's okay.
- Malah pergi lagi, hei. - Bu, sudah.
It's fine, I'll handle everything.
Sudah, nanti biar Tika saja yang belikan.
I'm going to the mosque.
Sekalian ke surau.
I'll see you later, Rudi.
Duluan ya, Aa.
Take care.
Hati-hati.
Here's your bag.
Tasmu, Dik.
Last night,
Semalam,
I felt like something was not right, Abuyya.
aku merasa ada yang tidak beres, Abuya.
I felt like something was trying to get into my house.
Aku merasa ada sesuatu yang berusaha masuk ke dalam rumahku.
Then I also heard Grandma's voice.
Terus aku juga dengar suara Oma.
But is that possible, Abuyya?
Tapi apa mungkin ya, Abuya,
That the spirit of the recently deceased can come to those closest to them
kalau arwah yang baru meninggal itu bisa datang ke orang terdekatnya
before 40 days?
sebelum 40 hari?
Islam is not familiar with the concept of spirits.
Islam itu tidak mengenal konsep arwah gentayangan.
Once someone dies and enters their grave,
Manusia, begitu dia wafat, masuk di dalam kubur,
they will answer questions from the angels.
dia sudah sibuk menjawab pertanyaan dari malaikat.
They'll be held accountable for all the deeds they did in this world.
Untuk mempertanggungjawabkan semua amal perbuatan
So, if you see a figure
Jadi, kalau Tika melihat ada sosok
who resembles someone you know has died,
yang mirip dengan orang yang Tika kenal yang sudah meninggal,
that's definitely the work of a jinn.
itu sudah pasti kerjaannya jin.
Ya-Sin.
Ya-Sin.
By the Quran, rich in wisdom!
Demi Al-Qur'an yang penuh hikmah,
You, O Prophet, are truly one of the messengers
sungguh engkau, Muhammad, adalah salah seorang dari rasul-rasul,
upon the Straight Path.
yang berada di atas jalan yang lurus,
This is a revelation from the Almighty, Most Merciful,
sebagai wahyu yang diturunkan oleh Allah Yang Mahaperkasa, Maha Penyayang,
so that you may warn a people
agar engkau memberi peringatan kepada suatu kaum
whose forefathers were not warned, and so are heedless.
yang nenek moyangnya belum pernah diberi peringatan, karena itu mereka lalai.
The decree of torment has already been justified against most of them,
Sungguh, pasti berlaku hukuman terhadap kebanyakan mereka,
Dad?
Bapak?
Mom?
Ibu?
Dean?
Dean?
Mom…
Bu…
Grandma,
Oma…
I miss you.
Dean kangen.
You're still here, right?
Oma masih di sini, 'kan?
Blood meets blood.
Darah bertemu darah.
Skin meets skin.
Kulit bertemu kulit.
Flesh meets flesh.
Daging bertemu daging.
Breech blocked by breech.
Sungsang terhalang oleh sungsang.
Black sky, black earth.
Langit hitam, bumi hitam.
I am controlled by my ancestors.
Aku dikendalikan oleh nenek moyangku.
All shall be destroyed before me.
Semua orang hancur di hadapanku.
Destroyed.
Hancur.
I call upon the Queen of Black Magic in the high mountains.
Aku meminta kepada Ratu Santet di gunung tinggi.
I know the Queen always desires something.
Aku tahu Ratu selalu menginginkan sesuatu.
I have brought her favorite offering.
Aku bawakan sesajen kesukaan Ratu.
Accept my command.
Terimalah perintahku
Destroy them all.
untuk menghancurkan semua orang ini.
What else do you want to tell me?
Oma mau bilang apa lagi sama Dean?
I…
I…
K…
K…
U…
U…
T…
T…
O…
O…
M…
A…
Ikut Oma? (Come with Grandma.)
Ikut Oma?
-Thank you. -You're welcome.
- Terima kasih, Pak. - Terima kasih.
Thank you, ma'am.
Terima kasih, Bu.
Tika!
Kak Tika!
Mom! Dad! Help!
Ibu! Bapak! Tolong!
Dean?
Dean?
Tika! Mom!
Kak Tika! Ibu!
Dad! Help!
Bapak! Tolong!
Dean?
Dean?
Mom! Dad!
Ibu! Bapak!
What is it?
Ada apa?
Dean?!
Dean?
Tika, what happened to your brother?
Tika, kenapa adikmu?
What happened?!
Kenapa?
-Dean? -Dean!
- Dean? - Dean!
Astaghfirullah.
Astagfirullah.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
This isn't all because of that shaman, right, Yul?
Ini semua bukan gara-gara ke dukun itu, bukan, Yul?
Your nephew didn't die because of what we did, right?
Keponakanmu meninggal bukan karena hal yang kita lakukan waktu itu, 'kan?
He is not my nephew.
Dia bukan keponakanku.
I wanted to help you because I know you are being bullied by them.
Aku membantumu karena aku tahu kau dijahati orang.
But not like this.
Tapi tidak kayak gini juga, Yul.
You're out of your mind, Yuli.
Sudah gila kau, Yul.
You were there from the start.
Kau ikut semuanya dari awal.
That means you are involved.
Berarti kau terlibat.
And what they are experiencing now is karma.
Dan balasan yang mereka terima sekarang adalah karma.
It's not because of me.
Bukan karena aku.
It's all my fault, Abuyya.
Semuanya salah aku, Abuya.
I should have talked him out of it.
Aku seharusnya bisa lebih menasihati Dean.
I should have just taken his board.
Seharusnya aku ambil saja papannya.
I should have checked his room straight away before the prayers.
Seharusnya aku langsung cek kamarnya untuk tahlilan.
Ask for forgiveness, Tika.
Istigfar, Tika.
I seek forgiveness from Allah the Almighty.
Astagfirullahaladzim.
I seek forgiveness from Allah.
Astagfirullah.
I feel like there's something evil directed towards my family.
Aku merasa ada sesuatu yang jahat sama keluargaku.
But I don't understand what it is.
Tapi aku tidak mengerti itu apa.
What should I do, Abuyya?
Aku harus bagaimana, Abuya?
The Prophet Muhammad was once bewitched
Rasulullah saw pernah disihir
by a woman using a knot that was tied up.
oleh seorang perempuan menggunakan buhul yang diikat.
Then the knot was placed under a stone
Lalu, buhul tersebut disimpan di bawah batu.
at the bottom of the Dzarwan well.
Di dasar sumur Dzarwan.
Then the Prophet ordered his companions to come and see the well the next day.
Lalu, Rasulullah memerintahkan sahabat untuk datang melihat sumur tersebut.
And coincidentally,
Dan bertepatan dengan itu…
Al-Mu'awwidzatain's revelation came down.
turunlah wahyu Al-Mu'awwidzatain.
Namely, the surahs Al-Falaq and An-Naas.
Yaitu surah Al-Falaq dan An-Naas.
At that time, they were recited by Rasulullah.
Saat itu dibacakan oleh Rasulullah.
Then, the rope that tied the binding knots
Lalu, tali yang mengikat buhul tersebut,
broke one by one, all eleven of them.
sebelas tali itu, putus satu demi satu.
Tonight, you should pray the Tahajjud prayer.
Nanti malam kau salat tahajud.
Perform your ablutions and pray.
Ambil wudu, salat,
Ask for forgiveness from Allah.
mohon ampun kepada Allah.
I intend to perform the Tahajjud prayer, two rak'ahs, for the sake of Allah.
Aku niat salat sunah Tahajud dua rakaat karena Allah ta'ala.
Allah is the Greatest.
Allahu Akbar.
Then after that, send prayers.
Lalu, setelah itu, kirim doa.
Ask Allah for protection.
Minta perlindungan kepada Allah.
O, Allah.
Ya Allah.
Please protect my parents…
Lindungilah kedua orang tua hamba,
Rudianto and Larasati
Rudianto dan Larasati,
from all danger and deceit.
dari segala mara bahaya dan tipu daya.
Amen.
Amin.
Hey.
Neng.
Wait.
Tunggu.
Laras.
Laras.
Where are you going?
Kau mau ke mana?
To the shop.
Toko.
To the shop?
Toko?
Don't you have a heart?
Kau punya perasaan tidak?
Our son just died.
Anak kita baru meninggal.
-Now you're going to work? -Then what should I do?
- Kau mau kerja? - Lalu, aku harus apa?
I've just lost my son.
Anakku habis meninggal.
I lost my mother too.
Ibu aku juga.
Tell me, what am I supposed to do?
Lalu, aku harus apa, Aa?
Be a mother, Laras.
Yah, jadi seperti ibunya, Laras.
It hasn't even been a day.
Belum satu hari lo.
There's no one to look after the shop.
Tidak ada yang jaga, Aa.
-Just ask Yono. -No, I can't.
- Suruh aja Yono. - Tidak bisa atuh.
I've told you many times, right?
Berkali-kali sudah dibilangin ya.
If you're putting something away, be careful, Rudi.
Kalau menaruh sesuatu, hati-hati, Aa Rudi.
Look what happened.
Ini jadinya kejadian.
Now it's broken.
Sayang itu pecah.
What's wrong? Let me see.
- Kenapa itu? Sini, diobati. - Tidak usah.
Fine, if you don't want my help.
Ya sudah kalau tidak mau ditolong.
Just leave it. Leave it.
Biarkan saja.
Let me put something on it so you can continue working.
Diperban dulu biar bisa lanjut kerja.
Thank you, Yul.
Terima kasih, Yul.
Just leave it.
Ditinggal saja.
I'll sort it out later.
Nanti aku yang bereskan.
What now?
Apalagi ini?
-I dropped these. -What's wrong with you, Yuli?
- Ini, Teh. - Astaga, Yuli.
You never get anything done when you work.
Kau bekerja tidak pernah benar.
All you do is make my life difficult.
Dari dulu kerjaannya cuma bisa menyusahkan hidupku saja.
-Because of you… -Enough, Ras!
- Gara-gara kau… - Sudah, Ras!
Why are you defending her?
Kok kau malah belain dia?
This should've been your job.
Ini juga seharusnya kerjaanmu.
That's enough.
Kau yang keterlaluan.
How can you say that to me?
Bisa ya sekarang kau bicara kayak gitu sama aku?
Is she using some kind of black magic on you?
Diguna-guna ya kau sama dia?
I'm just being honest, Ras.
Aku cuma bicara jujur, Ras.
Yuli has never fought back.
Dari dulu Yuli tidak pernah melawan.
Your family treats her like a maid
Kalian jadiin dia kayak pembantu.
even though she is family, right?
Padahal dia keluargamu, 'kan?
She is not family.
Dia bukan keluarga aku.
Then stop ordering her around.
Kalo gitu, berhenti suruh-suruh.
All you do is order people around.
Kau cuma bisanya merintah orang.
That's why you married me, right?
Bahkan kau menikahiku karena itu, 'kan?
Because I am poor.
Karena aku lebih miskin.
Stupid.
Bodoh.
You can push me around.
Bisa kau suruh-suruh.
"Rudi, lift that."
"Aa, itu angkat.
"Why did you put it there?"
Mengapa ditaruh di sana?
"Why aren't you getting smarter?"
Kok tidak pintar-pintar?"
I've never said that.
Aku tidak begitu.
Rudianto, you are so mean!
Rudianto, kau tega sama aku!
My son just died!
Anak aku baru meninggal!
Our son, Ras.
Anak kita, Ras.
You're not the only one grieving.
Bukan cuma kau yang merasa kehilangan.
I…
Aku…
Hang in there, Rudi.
Sabar ya, Aa.
I understand.
Aku mengerti.
She never does.
Dia tidak pernah mengerti.
Would you like to close up shop, ma'am?
Mau tutup sekarang, Bu?
Take me home.
Antar aku pulang ke rumah.
Rudi.
Aa.
If you could choose…
Kalau Aa Rudi bisa memilih…
would you stay with me?
Mau tidak sama aku terus?
Just leave Laras.
Tinggalkan saja atuh Teh Laras, Aa.
If you choose me,
Kalau Aa Rudi memilihku…
we will live happily together.
kita akan bisa hidup bahagia berdua.
Forever.
Selamanya.
I can't, Yuli.
Aku tidak bisa, Yul.
I have a family.
Aku masih punya keluarga.
Do you think Laras will take you back if she knows about this?
Kau pikir Teh Laras mau menerimamu lagi kalau dia tahu soal ini?
You're the one who seduced me.
Kau yang goda aku.
It turns out Laras was right.
Ternyata Laras benar.
You are just like your mother.
Kau seperti ibumu.
You're such an asshole.
Berengsek kau, Rudi.
Don't ever bring up my mother. My mother is not like that.
Jangan pernah bawa-bawa ibuku. Ibuku tidak seperti itu.
You're out of your mind, Yuli.
Gila kau, Yul.
Tika.
Tika.
Please don't tell your mother.
Tolong jangan bilang Ibu ya.
I'll explain it to her later.
Biar Bapak yang jelaskan.
There is no god but Allah, alone, without partner.
Tidak ada tuhan selain Allah, satu-satunya, tiada sekutu bagi-Nya.
His is the dominion and the praise. He gives life and causes death.
Milik-Nya segala kerajaan dan pujian.
There is no…
Tidak ada…
There is no god but Allah,
Tidak ada tuhan selain Allah,
alone, without partner.
satu-satunya, tiada sekutu bagi-Nya.
His is the dominion and the praise.
Milik-Nya segala kerajaan dan pujian.
He gives life and causes death.
Dia yang menghidupkan dan mematikan, dan Dia Maha Kuasa atas segala sesuatu.
Blood meets blood.
Darah bertemu darah.
Skin meets skin.
Kulit bertemu kulit.
Flesh meets flesh.
Daging bertemu daging.
There is no god but Allah.
Tidak ada tuhan selain Allah.
Breech blocked by breech.
Sungsang terhalang oleh sungsang.
Black sky, black earth.
Langit hitam, bumi hitam.
I am controlled by my ancestors.
Aku dikendalikan oleh nenek moyangku.
All shall be destroyed before me.
Semua orang hancur di hadapanku.
Destroyed.
Hancur, hancur, hancur.
There is no god but Allah.
Tidak ada tuhan selain Allah.
I call upon the Queen of Black Magic in the high mountains.
Aku meminta kepada Ratu Santet di gunung tinggi.
I know the Queen always desires something.
Aku tahu Ratu selalu menginginkan sesuatu.
I have brought her favorite offering.
Aku bawakan sesajen kesukaan Ratu.
I seek forgiveness from Allah the Almighty.
Astagfirullahaladzim.
There is no god but Allah, alone, without partner.
Tidak ada tuhan selain Allah, satu-satunya, tiada sekutu bagi-Nya.
Accept my command. Destroy…
Terimalah perintahku untuk menghancurkan…
His is the dominion and the praise. He gives life and causes death.
Milik-Nya segala kerajaan dan pujian.
…them all.
…semua orang ini.
Rudi?
Aa?
Tika! Help!
Tika! Tolong!
Please, Tika!
Tolong, Tika!
Help!
Tolong!
-Rudi? -Help!
- Aa? - Tolong!
Please, Tika!
Tolong. Tika!
Laras!
Laras!
This prayer will have four takbirs,
Salat jenazah ini akan ada empat takbir,
and in each takbir, there is no bowing or prostration.
lalu masing-masing takbir tidak ada ruku dan sujud.
Ending with a salaam, all right?
Diakhiri dengan salam, ya?
Let's begin.
Kita mulai.
I intend to perform the funeral prayer for this deceased man, with four takbirs…
Aku niat salat jenazah atas mayat ini, empat takbir…
Allah is the Greatest.
Allahu Akbar.
O Allah, forgive him, have mercy on him, grant him peace, and pardon him.
Ya Allah, ampunilah dia, rahmatilah dia, sejahterakanlah dia, dan maafkanlah dia.
Allah is the Greatest.
Allahu Akbar.
Peace be upon you, and the mercy of Allah.
Assalamualaikum warahmatullah.
Peace be upon you…
Assalamualaikum…
Oh God.
Astagfirullahaladzim.
Tika?
Tika?
Please get her a drink.
Tolong ambilkan minum.
Come on, get some water.
Ambilkan minum ayo.
Oh my God!
Astagfirullah…
Oh God. Tika.
Astagfirullahaladzim, Tika.
Ask for forgiveness, Tika.
Istigfar, Tika.
I seek forgiveness from Allah the Almighty.
Astagfirullahaladzim.
Allah.
Allah…
Tika. Drink.
Tika, ayo.
Tika…
Tika…
Mom.
Bu.
This can't be a coincidence, Mom.
Ini tidak mungkin kebetulan, Bu.
Dad, Dean, Grandma.
Bapak, Dean, Oma.
-Abuyya also told me… -That's enough.
- Abuya juga bilang ke Tika… - Sudah.
Enough.
Cukup.
Don't talk about things that don't make sense.
Tidak usah bicarakan hal-hal yang tidak masuk akal.
That's enough.
Sudah.
But someone is harming us, Mom.
Tapi kita dijahati sama orang, Bu.
We have to do something.
Kita harus melakukan sesuatu.
Please listen to me.
Tika mohon.
Just this once, will you believe me, Mom?
Sekali ini saja percaya sama Tika ya, Bu?
I…
Tika…
I don't want to lose anyone else, Mom.
Tika tidak mau merasakan kehilangan lagi, Bu.
You're all I have left.
Tika tinggal cuma punya Ibu.
I don't have anyone else.
Tika tidak punya siapa-siapa lagi.
I'm scared.
Tika takut.
It is true that
Memang…
if we claim to have faith,
kalau kita mengaku beriman,
surely Allah will test it.
pasti Allah akan uji keimanan kita.
With a feeling of fear, a feeling of worry,
Dengan perasaan takut, perasaan khawatir…
We will certainly test you with a touch of fear and famine
"Kami pasti akan mengujimu dengan sedikit ketakutan dan kelaparan,
and loss of property, life, and crops.
kekurangan harta, jiwa, dan buah-buahan."
Allah will even test us with a lack of wealth.
Bahkan Allah akan uji kita dengan kekurangan harta.
Allah tests us by taking the people we love.
Allah uji kita dengan kehilangan orang-orang yang kita sayang.
Parents, younger siblings, older siblings.
Orang tua, adik, kakak.
Be patient, all right?
Kau yang sabar, ya.
Remember,
Ingat.
Allah will not test His servants
Allah tidak akan menguji hamba-Nya
beyond the limits of their ability.
melebihi batas kemampuan hamba-Nya.
Amen.
Amin.
Yuli?
Yul?
Why is this here?
Kenapa ini bisa ada di sini?
You can figure it out yourself.
Bisa mikir sendiri, 'kan?
Rudi never loved you.
Rudi itu tidak pernah cinta sama kau.
He was just scared of you.
Dia cuma takut.
How dare you?
Kurang ajar kau, Yul.
It was you, right? You're the one who seduced him!
Pasti kau, 'kan? Kau yang goda dia?
And you're the one who killed my whole family.
Jangan-jangan kau yang buat semua keluargaku meninggal.
Damn you.
Dasar kau.
You bastard child.
Anak selingkuhan.
You're a slut, just like your mother!
Perempuan murahan sama saja kayak ibumu!
You're all tough now, aren't you?
Berani kau sekarang sama aku, Yul?
You dare to go against me?
Berani kau sama aku sekarang, Yuli?
Yes, I'm going against you.
Ya. Ya, aku berani sama kau.
Why should I be afraid? Who do you think you are?
Kenapa aku harus takut? Kau siapa?
You are the bastard child, not me.
Kau yang anak selingkuhan, bukan aku.
What?
Apa?
-Trash. -You're trash.
- Sampah kau. - Kau yang sampah.
-Bastard. -You're the bastard!
- Anak haram. - Kau yang anak haram!
You have taken all my happiness, Yuli.
Kau ambil semua kebahagiaan aku, Yuli.
-You ruined my life. -That should have been my life!
- Kau hancurkan hidup aku. - Itu harusnya hidupku!
You should be the one dead!
Harusnya kau yang mati!
-Get out of here! -You go!
- Pergi kau dari sini! - Kau yang pergi!
-Get out of here. -This is still my house!
- Pergi kau dari sini. - Ini masih rumah aku!
-Get out of here! -This is my house!
- Pergi kau dari sini! - Ini rumah aku!
You're just like your mother!
Ibu sama anak sama saja!
Laras, open the door.
Laras, buka.
Laras, open up!
Laras, buka!
You are all evil!
Kalian jahat!
You've been mean to me from the start.
Dari dulu kalian jahat sama aku.
How long do you want to live like this?
Mau sampai kapan kalian kayak gini?
Laras, listen to me.
Ras, dengar aku.
Don't you realize?
Kau itu tidak sadar.
You're the one who caused all your family to die!
Kau yang membuat semua keluargamu mati!
Our lives are the same now, Ras.
Hidup kita sama sekarang, Ras.
The same.
Sama.
We're both ruined!
Sama-sama hancur!
Yono.
Yono.
What did you say to Tika?
Bicara apa kau sama si Tika?
I didn't say anything.
Tidak bicara apa-apa kok.
You didn't say anything?
"Tidak bicara apa-apa kok".
What did you say?
Bicara apa? Cepat.
Leave me out of this, Yuli.
Aku sudah tidak mau ikut-ikut lagi, Yul.
What did Tika give you?
Dikasih apa kau sama si Tika?
Did you tell her about me?
Kau laporkan aku?
Did you tell her that I did everything?
Bilang kalau semuanya aku yang lakukan?
Admit it.
- Mengaku kau. - Aku tidak bicara apa-apa, Yul.
Not everyone is as mean as you, Yul.
Tidak semua orang tega kayak kau, Yul.
Destroyed.
Hancur, hancur, hancur.
I call upon the Queen of Black Magic in the high mountains.
Aku meminta kepada Ratu Santet di gunung tinggi.
I know the Queen always desires something.
Aku tahu Ratu selalu menginginkan sesuatu.
I have brought
Aku bawakan sesajen
her favorite offering.
kesukaan Ratu.
Accept my command.
Terimalah perintahku untuk menghancurkan semua orang ini.
Who's that?
Siapa itu?
Who's there?
Siapa?
Stop messing around!
Jangan bercanda!
Help!
Tolong!
-Mrs. Laras! -Ma'am!
Bu Laras!
It's Mr. Yono, ma'am!
Itu, Bu, Pak Yono!
-Ma'am, Mr. Yono, ma'am. -At your shop, ma'am.
- Bu, Pak Yono. - Di tokonya, Bu.
-Oh God! -Please step back.
- Astagfirullah. - Tolong mundur ya.
Please, step back, step back. Stay behind the police line.
Tolong ya, mundur.
Excuse me, sorry.
Permisi, punten.
Excuse me.
Punten.
-Ma'am, don't come in. -I own the shop, sir.
- Bu, jangan masuk. - Aku yang punya toko, Pak.
All right, ma'am.
Ya, silakan, Bu.
Oh my God!
Astagfirullah!
Mom? Mom!
Ibu? Ibu!
Mom.
Ibu.
Mom…
Ibu…
-Poor Mr. Yono. -I can't believe it.
- Kasihan banget Pak Yono. - Tidak menyangka ya.
His head…
Ya, kepalanya itu…
Mom?
Ibu?
No, Mom, don't!
Jangan, Bu!
All of you
Kalian semua
will die.
akan mati.
Allah! There is no deity except Him, the Ever-Living, the Sustainer of existence.
Allah, tidak ada Tuhan yang berhak disembah melainkan Dia,
Neither drowsiness overtakes Him nor sleep.
Tidak mengantuk dan tidak tidur.
To Him belongs whatever is in the heavens and whatever is on the earth.
Kepunyaan-Nya apa yang di langit dan di bumi.
Who is it that can intercede with Him except by His permission?
Tiada yang dapat memberi syafaat di sisi-Nya tanpa izin-Nya.
He knows what is [presently] before them and what will be after them,
Dia mengetahui apa yang ada di hadapan dan di belakang mereka.
and they encompass not a thing of His knowledge except for what He wills.
Dan mereka tidak mengetahui apa pun tentang ilmu-Nya
His throne extends over the heavens and the earth,
Kursi-Nya meliputi langit dan bumi.
and their preservation does not tire Him.
Dan Dia tidak merasa berat memelihara keduanya.
And He is the Most High, the Most Great.
Dan Dia Maha Tinggi, Maha Agung.
Where are
Mana lagi doa-doamu yang lain?
Abuyya?
Abuya?
Abuyya, please help me.
Abuya tolong Tika, Abuya.
My mom, she's…
Ibu…
Mom! Don't, Mom!
Ibu!
In the name of Allah,
Dengan nama Allah, yang dengan nama-Nya,
with whose name nothing on earth or in the heavens can cause harm.
tidak ada sesuatu pun di bumi maupun di langit yang dapat membahayakan.
And He is the All-Hearing, the All-Knowing.
Dan Dia Maha Mendengar, Maha Mengetahui.
We'll take your mother to the mosque.
Kita bawa ibumu ke surau.
Come on.
Ayo.
Come on, be careful.
Ayo, hati-hati.
Don't rush.
Jangan terburu-buru bawanya.
Oh God!
Astagfirullahaladzim!
Grandma…
Oma…
Don't mention your God's name here.
Jangan sebut nama tuhanmu di sini.
Aunt Yuli?
Bi Yuli?
What's the matter, Tika?
Kenapa, Tika?
Yes.
Ya.
I killed all your family.
Aku yang bunuh semua keluargamu.
They all deserved this.
Mereka semua pantas menerima semua ini.
Even Dean?
Dean, Bi?
My dad?
Bapak?
-My mom now, because of you? -Everyone.
- Ibu sekarang juga karena Bibi? - Semuanya.
Your family is evil, Tika.
Keluargamu itu jahat, Tika.
Since I was little,
Dari aku kecil,
I have never been treated well by your family.
aku tidak pernah mendapatkan perlakuan yang sepantasnya dari keluargamu.
They called me a bastard child.
Aku selalu dibilang anak selingkuhan.
I'm not.
Aku bukan anak selingkuhan.
Your grandmother lied.
Omamu yang memutarbalikkan fakta.
She took everything I had, Tika.
Dia ambil semua yang aku punya, Tika.
She killed my parents using black magic.
Dia santet orang tuaku sampai mati!
She took my house.
Dia ambil rumahku dan orang tuaku.
My life was ruined!
Hidupku hancur!
Your parents deserved to die!
Bapak dan ibumu layak mati!
I'll never regret doing it with my own hands.
Aku tidak pernah menyesal melakukannya.
Why didn't you ever tell me?
Kenapa Bibi tidak pernah bilang ke Tika?
Auntie, we are a family.
Bi, kita ini satu keluarga, Bi.
You're such a good girl.
Anak baik.
-Am I family? -Of course!
- Aku keluargamu? - Tentu saja!
-Yes, Auntie… -Every day, you saw me being tormented.
- Ya, Bibi… - Tiap hari kau lihat aku disiksa.
I was insulted by your mother. By your grandmother.
Aku dihina sama ibumu, sama omamu.
And what did you do?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
Answer me! What did you do?
Jawab aku, apa yang kau lakukan?
-I had no choice-- -You pretend to be so pious.
- Tika tidak punya pilihan. - Sok paling beragama.
But you never stood up for me!
Tapi kau tidak pernah membela aku!
You are a hypocrite.
Munafik kau.
You and your family deserve to die.
Kau dan keluargamu itu pantas untuk mati.
You're cruel!
Bibi tega!
That's how it feels to be me.
Itu rasanya jadi aku.
I will never be like you.
Tika tidak bakal kayak Bibi.
-Destroyed, right? -No.
- Hancur, 'kan? - Tidak.
Mom…
Ibu…
Come on, continue.
Ayo, lanjut.
Step back. Join them over there.
Kau mundur, kau gabung di sana.
I seek forgiveness from Allah the Almighty.
Astagfirullahaladzim.
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
O Allah, You come from peace and from you comes peace,
Ya Allah, Engkaulah sumber keselamatan, dan dari-Mu-lah datang keselamatan,
and may peace be upon you.
dan kepada-Mu-lah kembali segala keselamatan.
Blessed are You, o owner of majesty and honor.
Maha Suci Engkau, wahai Tuhan yang memiliki keagungan dan kemuliaan.
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, I perform an exorcism for you
Dengan nama Allah, aku membacakan rukiah untukmu
from everything that harms you,
dari segala sesuatu yang menyakitimu,
from the evil of every soul or envious eye.
dari kejahatan setiap jiwa atau mata yang dengki.
May Allah heal you.
Semoga Allah menyembuhkanmu.
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
Say, O Prophet, "O Allah! Lord over all authorities!
Katakanlah Muhammad, "Wahai Tuhan pemilik kekuasaan,
You honor whoever You please and disgrace who You please.
Engkau muliakan siapa pun yang Engkau kehendaki
All good is in Your Hands. Surely You alone are Most Capable of everything.
dan Engkau hinakan siapa pun yang Engkau kehendaki.
You cause the night to pass into the day and the day into the night.
Engkau masukkan malam ke dalam siang
You bring forth the living from the dead and the dead from the living.
Dan Engkau keluarkan yang hidup dari yang mati,
And You provide for whoever You will without limit."
Dan Engkau berikan rezeki
In the name of Allah, Allah is the Greatest.
Bismillahi Allahu Akbar.
Mom!
Ibu!
Blood meets blood.
Darah bertemu darah.
Skin meets skin.
Kulit bertemu kulit.
Flesh meets flesh.
Daging bertemu daging.
Breech blocked by breech.
Sungsang terhalang oleh sungsang.
I am controlled by my ancestors.
Aku dikendalikan oleh nenek moyangku.
All shall be destroyed before me.
Semua orang hancur di hadapanku.
Stay out of it, or you will be destroyed!
Jangan ikut campur atau kalian akan hancur!
Indeed, it is from Solomon,
- Hancur, hancur! - Innahu min Sulaimana wa innahu
Oh God!
Astagfirullahaladzim!
Destroyed.
Hancur.
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
Say, O Prophet,
Katakanlah Muhammad, "Telah diwahyukan kepadaku
I call upon…
Aku meminta…
I call upon the Queen of Black Magic.
Aku meminta kepada Ratu Santet di gunung tinggi.
"…and said to their fellow jinn, indeed, we have heard a wondrous recitation.
Lalu mereka berkata,
It leads to Right Guidance."
yang memberi petunjuk kepada jalan yang benar.
I call upon the Queen of Black Magic in the high mountains.
Aku meminta kepada Ratu Santet di gunung tinggi.
"…so we believed in it,
Lalu, kami beriman kepadanya.
and we will never associate anyone with our Lord in worship."
Dan kami sekali-kali tidak akan mempersekutukan
I know…
Aku tahu…
"Now, we believe that our Lord, Exalted is His Majesty,
Dan sesungguhnya Mahatinggi keagungan Tuhan kami,
has neither a mate nor offspring…
Dia tidak beristri dan tidak beranak."
and that the foolish of us used to utter outrageous falsehoods about Allah."
Dan sesungguhnya orang yang bodoh di antara kami dahulu
"We certainly thought that humans and jinn would never speak lies about Allah."
dan sesungguhnya kami mengira bahwa manusia dan jin itu
"And some men used to seek refuge with some jinn,
dan sesungguhnya ada beberapa manusia
so they increased each other in wickedness."
tetapi jin menjadikan manusia bertambah sesat.
In the name of Allah, Allah is the Greatest.
Bismillahi Allahu Akbar.
Allah is Sufficient for us, and He is the Best Disposer of affairs.
Cukuplah Allah bagi kami, dan Dia sebaik-baik Pengatur urusan.
Mom?
Ibu?
-Astaghfirullahaladzim. -Mom?
- Astagfirullahaladzim. - Ibu?
Mom?
Ibu?
Come on, help her up.
Ayo bantu, dipapah.
Continue the prayers.
Tolong dibantu doa.
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
Say, O Prophet, He is Allah. One and Indivisible.
Katakanlah Muhammad, Dialah Allah, Yang Maha Esa.
Allah, the Sustainer, needed by all.
Allah tempat meminta segala sesuatu.
He has never had offspring, nor was He born,
Allah tidak beranak dan tidak pula diperanakkan.
and there is none comparable to Him.
Dan tidak ada sesuatu yang setara dengan Dia.
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
from the evil of whatever He has created,
dari kejahatan makhluk yang Dia ciptakan,
and from the evil of the night when it grows dark,
dan dari kejahatan malam apabila telah gelap gulita,
and from the evil of those witches casting spells by blowing onto knots,
dan dari kejahatan perempuan-perempuan penyihir yang meniup pada buhul-buhul,
and from the evil of an envier when they envy.
dan dari kejahatan orang yang dengki apabila dia dengki.
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
Say, O Prophet, I seek refuge in the Lord of humankind,
Katakanlah, Aku berlindung kepada Tuhannya manusia,
the Master of humankind, the God of humankind,
Raja manusia,
from the evil of the lurking whisperer, who whispers into the hearts of humankind,
dari kejahatan bisikan setan yang bersembunyi,
from among jinn and humankind.
dari golongan jin dan manusia.
Enough, Tika! Enough.
Sudah, Tika, sudah.
-Get some water. -Enough!
Ambil air minum.
Enough, Tika.
Sudah, Tika.
Tika.
Tika.
Pray for your mom.
Doakan Ibu.
Let her go.
Ikhlas.
My Lord, forgive me and my parents,
Ya Tuhanku, ampunilah aku dan kedua orang tuaku,
and have mercy on them as they raised me when I was small.
dan sayangilah mereka
Help!
Ampun!
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
Aku berlindung kepada Allah dari setan yang terkutuk.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
In Your Name, we repel enemies from all directions.
Dengan namaMu kami menolak musuh-musuh dari segala arah.
In the name of Allah, we pelt them from afar into disarray.
Dengan nama Allah kami melempari mereka jauh dengan keceraiberaian.
You are my hope, O God and my Master.
Engkau adalah tempat aku berharap, Ya Tuhanku.
If they intend evil against me, then let them boil.
Bila mereka bermaksud jahat kepadaku, maka mendidihlah mereka.
In the name of Allah, Allah is the Greatest!
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.
O Allah…
Ya Allah…
May God forgive her sins.
Semoga Tuhan mengampuni dosa-dosanya.
Mom?
Ibu?
Mom…
Ibu…
Mom, it's me, Tika, Mom.
Ibu, ini Tika.
It's Tika.
Ini Tika.
Mrs. Laras?
Bu Laras?
-Seek forgiveness. -Mom!
- Istigfar. - Ibu.
I seek forgiveness from Allah the Almighty.
Astagfirullahaladzim.
I… I seek…
As… Astag…
I seek forgiveness from Allah the Almighty.
Astagfirullahaladzim.
It's okay.
Tidak apa-apa.
There is no god but Allah, and Muhammad is the messenger of Allah.
La ilaaha illallah Muhammadurrasuulullah.
Mom?
Ibu?
Indeed, we belong to Allah, and to Him we shall return.
Innalillahi wa inna ilaihi rajiun.
Mom!
Ibu!
Mom, don't leave me!
Ibu, jangan tinggalkan Tika!
Mom, wake up!
Ibu, bangun!
-Tika? -Yes?
- Tika? - Ya?
-I have to go. -Okay.
- Abuya pamit dulu ya. - Ya.
Thank you, Abuyya.
Terima kasih ya, Abuya.
Stay strong, okay?
Yang sabar, ya?
I will.
Ya.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
And upon you too.
Alaikum salam.
-Hang in there. -Thank you.
- Duluan ya, Tik. - Terima kasih ya.
-See you. -Bye.
- Duluan. - Ya.
-Peace be upon you. -And upon you too.
- Asalamualaikum. - Alaikum salam.
May Allah give me strength to do all this.
Semoga Allah memberi Tika kekuatan untuk menjalani ini semua.
In the name of Allah, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Dengan menyebut nama Allah Yang Maha Pengasih lagi Maha Penyayang.